A few years ago,
منذ بضع سنوات.
my mom developed rheumatoid arthritis.
أصيبت أمي بالتهاب المفاصل الروماتيزمي.
Her wrists, knees and toes swelled up, causing crippling, chronic pain.
تورّمت مفاصل الرسغين والرُكبتين والأصابع لديها، مُسببة ألما مزمنا.
She had to file for disability.
وكان يجب أن يتم إدراحها كمُعاقة.
She stopped attending our local mosque.
توقفت عن الذهاب للمسجد المحلي لدينا.
Some mornings it was too painful for her to brush her teeth.
في بعض الأيام، كان يؤلمها جدًا أن تنظف أسنانها.
I wanted to help.
كنت أريد المساعدة
But I didn't know how.
ولكني لم أعلم كيف
I'm not a doctor.
أنا لست طبيب
So, what I am is a historian of medicine.
أنا مؤرخ للطب.
So I started to research the history of chronic pain.
لذلك، بدأت أبحث في تاريخ الألم المزمن.
Turns out, UCLA has an entire history of pain collection
واتضح لي أن جامعة كاليفورنيا، لوس أنجلوس لديهم تاريخ متكامل عن مجموعة من الآلام
in their archives.
في أرشيفاتهم
And I found a story -- a fantastic story --
ووجدت قصة.. قصة مذهلة
of a man who saved -- rescued -- millions of people from pain;
عن رجل أنقذ الملايين من الناس من الألم..
people like my mom.
أناس مثل أمي.
Yet, I had never heard of him.
ولكني لم أكن قد سمعت عنه بعد.
There were no biographies of him, no Hollywood movies.
لم يكن هناك سير ذاتية عنه. ولا أفلام هوليوودية
His name was John J. Bonica.
كان اسمه جون ج. بونيكا.
But when our story begins,
ولكن عندما بدأت قصتنا،
he was better known as Johnny "Bull" Walker.
كان يُعرف أفضل بـ جوني "بول" والكرز
It was a summer day in 1941.
كان يومًا صيفيًا في 1941
The circus had just arrived in the tiny town of Brookfield, New York.
وقد وصل السيرك للتو إلى مدينة بروكفيلد الصغيرة، نيويورك
Spectators flocked to see the wire-walkers, the tramp clowns --
تدفق المتفرجين ليشاهدوا السائرين على الأسلاك، المهرجين المُشرّدين
if they were lucky, the human cannonball.
وإن كانوا محظوظين: الصواريخ البشرية.
They also came to see the strongman, Johnny "Bull" Walker,
وجاءوا أيضًا ليشاهدوا الرجل القوي: جوني "بول" والكر
a brawny bully who'd pin you for a dollar.
البلطجي مفتول العضلات الذي قد يفتك بك من أجل دولار.
You know, on that particular day, a voice rang out
تعلمون، في هذا اليوم خصيصًا، صدح صوت ما
over the circus P.A. system.
في أرجاء نظام السيرك
They needed a doctor urgently, in the live animal tent.
لقد احتاجوا لطبيب على وجه السرعة في خيمة الحيوانات الحية
Something had gone wrong with the lion tamer.
حدث خطب ما لمروض الأسود
The climax of his act had gone wrong,
الجزء الأخير من عرضه لم يتم جيدًا
and his head was stuck inside the lion's mouth.
ورأسه حُشرت داخل فم الأسد.
He was running out of air;
وبدا ينفذ من حوله الهواء
the crowd watched in horror
الحشد أخذ يشاهده في فزع
as he struggled and then passed out.
وهو يصارع ثم وهو يفقد الوعي
When the lion finally did relax its jaws,
أخيرًا عندما أرخَى الأسد فكيه،
the lion tamer just slumped to the ground, motionless.
انزلق المروض إلى الأرض، بلا حراك
When he came to a few minutes later,
وعندما عاد للوعي بعد بضع دقائق
he saw a familiar figure hunched over him.
رأى وجهًا مألوفًا ينحني عليه
It was Bull Walker.
لقد كان بول والكر
The strongman had given the lion tamer mouth-to-mouth, and saved his life.
الرجل القوي أعطى مروض الأسود تنفسًا صناعيًا بالفم وأنقذ حياته
Now, the strongman hadn't told anyone,
والآن، هذا الرجل القوي لم يخبر أحدًا
but he was actually a third-year medical student.
ولكنه حقيقةً كان طالبًا يدرس الطب في عامه الثالث
He toured with the circus during summers to pay tuition,
كان يتجول مع السيرك في الصيف ليدفع لدروسه
but kept it a secret to protect his persona.
ولكنه أبقاه سرًا ليحفظ شخصيته
He was supposed to be a brute, a villain --
كان مفترضًا أن يكون وحشيا، وغدا
not a nerdy do-gooder.
ليس مجتهدًا يفعل الخير
His medical colleagues didn't know his secret, either.
لم يعرف زملاؤه في الطب سره أيضًا
As he put it, "If you were an athlete, you were a dumb dodo."
لأنه اعتقد أن "إذا كنت رياضيًا، فأنت شخص أحمق"
So he didn't tell them about the circus,
لذلك فهو لم يخبرهم عن السيرك
or about how he wrestled professionally on evenings and weekends.
ولا عن أنه كيف يصارع باحتراف في الأمسيات وفي العطلات.
He used a pseudonym like Bull Walker,
واستخدم اسمًا مستعارًا مثل بول والكر
or later, the Masked Marvel.
أو لاحقًا: المعجزة المُقنع
He even kept it a secret that same year,
وأخفى سره أيضًا في ذاك العام
when he was crowned the Light Heavyweight Champion
الذي توج فيه بطلًا للأوزان الخفيفة
of the world.
على مستوى العالم.
Over the years, John J. Bonica lived these parallel lives.
وعلى مر السنوات، عاش جون ج. بونيكا هذين العالمين المتوازيين
He was a wrestler;
كان مصارعًا
he was a doctor.
وكان طبيبًا.
He was a heel;
كان معالجًا
he was a hero.
وكان بطلًا
He inflicted pain,
تسبب في الألم
and he treated it.
وعالجه.
And he didn’t know it at the time, but over the next five decades,
ولم يكن يعلم في حينها، ولكن طوال الخمس عقود التالية
he'd draw on these dueling identities
كان عليه أن يستخدم هذه الهوية المزدوجة
to forge a whole new way to think about pain.
لصياغة طريقة جديدة كليًا للتفكير في الألم.
It'd change modern medicine so much so, that decades later,
هذه الطريقة ستغير الطب الحديث كثيرًا، لدرجة أن بعد عدة عقود،
Time magazine would call him pain relief's founding father.
مجلة التايم أطلقت عليه الأب الروحي لتأسيس مسكنات الألم
But that all happened later.
ولكن كل هذا حدث مؤخرًا
In 1942, Bonica graduated medical school and married Emma,
في عام 1942، تخرج بونيكا من كلية الطب وتزوج من إيما
his sweetheart, whom he had met at one of his matches years before.
حبيبته التي التقى بها في أحدى مبارياته قبل عدة سنوات
He still wrestled in secret -- he had to.
ظل يصارع في السر، كان مضطرًا.
His internship at New York's St. Vincent's Hospital paid nothing.
فترته التدريبية في مستشفى القس فنسنت بنيويورك لم تجلب له المال الكافي
With his championship belt, he wrestled in big-ticket venues,
أخذ يصارع بحزام البطولة في أماكن ذات تذاكر بقيمة كبيرة
like Madison Square Garden,
مثل حديقة سكوير ماديسون،
against big-time opponents,
ضد منافسين كبار
like Everett "The Blonde Bear" Marshall,
مثل إفريت "الدب الأشقر" مارشال
or three-time world champion, Angelo Savoldi.
أو بطل العالم لثلاث مرات، أنجيلو سافولدي.
The matches took a toll on his body;
المباريات سببت تشوهات في جسده
he tore hip joints, fractured ribs.
لقد مزق مفصل الورك و كسر ضلوعًا.
One night, The Terrible Turk's big toe scratched a scar like Capone's
ذات ليلة، تسبب الإصبع الكبير ل "التركي المروع" في ندبة مثل ندبة كابون
down the side of his face.
أسفل على جانب وجهه.
The next morning at work, he had to wear a surgical mask to hide it.
في الصباح التالي كان عليه أن يرتدي قناع جراحة كي يخفيها.
Twice Bonica showed up to the O.R. with one eye so bruised,
دخل بونيكا مرتين إلى غرفة الجراحة بعين مكدومة
he couldn't see out of it.
ولم يتمكن من الرؤية خلالها
But worst of all were his mangled cauliflower ears.
ولكن الأسوء كانت أذنيه المهترئتين التي كانت تشبه القرنبيط.
He said they felt like two baseballs on the sides of his head.
كان يقول أنه شعر بهما كأنهما طابتين على جانبي وجهه
Pain just kept accumulating in his life.
تواصل تراكم الألم في حياته.
Next, he watched his wife go into labor at his hospital.
بعدها، شاهد زوجته و هي تدخل المستشفى للولادة
She heaved and pushed, clearly in anguish.
كانت تئن وتدفع متألمة بوضوح
Her obstetrician called out to the intern on duty
قام الطبيب بمناداة الطبيب المتدرب على وجه السرعة
to give her a few drops of ether to ease her pain.
ليعطيها بضع قطرات من الكحول لتخفيف ألمها
But the intern was a young guy, just three weeks on the job --
ولكن الطبيب المتدرب كان شابًا يافعًا لم يقض 3 أسابيع في الوظيفة
he was jittery, and in applying the ether,
كان متوترًا و أثناء حقنها بالكحول،
irritated Emma's throat.
تهيجت حنجرة إيما.
She vomited and choked, and started to turn blue.
فتقيأت واختنقت، وبدأ لونها يشحب
Bonica, who was watching all this, pushed the intern out of the way,
بونيكا الذي كان يشاهد كل هذا قام بدفع الطبيب المتدرب بعيدًا عن طريقه
cleared her airway,
وقام بتنقية مسار الهواء لها
and saved his wife and his unborn daughter.
وأنقذ حياة زوجته وابنته التي لم تولد بعد
At that moment, he decided to devote his life to anesthesiology.
في تلك اللحظة، قرر بونيكا أن يوهب حياته لعلم التخدير.
Later, he'd even go on to help develop the epidural, for delivering mothers.
لاحقًا، سوف يساعد في تطوير المسكنات الفوق الجافية للسيدات القادمات للولادة
But before he could focus on obstetrics,
ولكن قبل أن يركز على علم التوليد
Bonica had to report for basic training.
كان عليه أن يتقدم للتدريب العام.
Right around D-Day,
طوال اليوم
Bonica showed up to Madigan Army Medical Center,
ظهر بونيكا في المركز الطبي العسكري بماديجان
near Tacoma.
قرب تاكوما
At 7,700 beds, it was one of the largest army hospitals in America.
كان واحدًا من أكبر المستشفيات العسكرية في أمريكا بحوالي 7,700 سرير.
Bonica was in charge of all pain control there.
بونيكا كان مسئولًا عن كل ما هو متعلق بالتحكم بالألم هناك
He was only 27.
كان عمره 27 عامًا فقط
Treating so many patients, Bonica started noticing cases
وبمعالجته للعديد من المرضى، بدأ بونيكا بملاحظة الحالات
that contradicted everything he had learned.
التي عارضت كل ما قد تعلمه.
Pain was supposed to be a kind of alarm bell -- in a good way --
كان من المفترض أن يكون الألم نوعًا من جرس إنذار.. بطريقة جيدة.
a body's way of signaling an injury, like a broken arm.
طريقة الجسم في الإشارة للإصابة، مثل ذراع مكسور.
But in some cases,
ولكن في بعض الحالات
like after a patient had a leg amputated,
بعد القيام ببتر ساق مريض
that patient might still complain of pain in that nonexistent leg.
كان المريض لايزال يشكو من الألم في القدم الغير موجودة.
But if the injury had been treated, why would the alarm bell keep ringing?
ولكن إذا كان قد تمت معالجة الألم، لماذا ظل جرس الانذار يرن؟
There were other cases in which there was no evidence of an injury whatsoever,
وكان هناك حالات أخرى حيث لم يكن هناك دليل على الاصابة أو ما شابه
and yet, still the patient hurt.
ولكن مازال المريض يشعر بالألم.
Bonica tracked down all the specialists at his hospital -- surgeons,
تعقب بونيكا كل المختصين في المشفى.. الجراحين،
neurologists, psychiatrists, others.
أطباء الأعصاب، الأطباء النفسيين، وآخرين.
And he tried to get their opinions on his patients.
وحاول أن يأخذ رأيهم في مرضاه
It took too long, so he started organizing group meetings over lunch.
واستغرق هذا وقتًا طويلا، لذلك بدأ بتنظيم اجتماعات على الغداء.
It would be like a tag team of specialists going up against the patient's pain.
كانت أشبه برابطة من المختصين هدفها مواجهة ألم المريض.
No one had ever focused on pain this way before.
لم يسبق وأن تناول أحد الألم بهذه الطريقة من قبل
After that, he hit the books.
بعد ذلك، عكف على الكتب
He read every medical textbook he could get his hands on,
قرأ كل كتاب طبي قد يقع في متناوله
carefully noting every mention of the word "pain."
مدونًا بعناية كل موضع ذكر فيه كلمة "ألم"
Out of the 14,000 pages he read,
ومن بين 14,000 صفحة قرأها
the word "pain" was on 17 and a half of them.
ذُكرت كلمة "ألم" في 17 ونصف منهم
Seventeen and a half.
سبعة عشر ونصف!
For the most basic, most common, most frustrating part of being a patient.
عن الجزء الأكثر أساسية، الأكثر شيوعًا، و الأكثر صعوبة لكونك مريض.
Bonica was shocked -- I'm quoting him,
بونيكا كان مصدوما.. أنا أتحدث بلسانه،
he said, "What the hell kind of conclusion can you come to there?
فقد قال، "ما هذا الإستنتاج بحق الجحيم الذي قد يخلصون به؟
The most important thing from the patient's perspective,
الجزء الأكثر أهمية من وجهة نظر المريض
they don't talk about."
هم لا يتحدثون عنه"
So over the next eight years, Bonica would talk about it.
لذلك بدأ بونيكا في الثمان سنوات التالية بالتحدث عنه.
He'd write about it; he'd write those missing pages.
بدأ يكتب عنه، بدأ بكتابة الصفحات المفقودة.
He wrote what would later be known as the Bible of Pain.
لقد قام بكتابة ما عُرف بعد ذلك بالكتاب المقدس للألم
In it he proposed new strategies,
اقترح فيه خططا جديدة
new treatments using nerve-block injections.
علاجات جديدة باستخدام حُقن خدر العصب.
He proposed a new institution, the Pain Clinic,
اقترح معهدا جديدا وهو عيادة الألم
based on those lunchtime meetings.
مرتكزة على اجتماعات الغداء.
But the most important thing about his book
ولكن أهم شيء في كتابه
was that it was kind of an emotional alarm bell for medicine.
هو أنه كان نوعًا من جرس إنذار عاطفي للطب
A desperate plea to doctors to take pain seriously
التماس يائس للأطباء لأخذ الألم بعين الجدية
in patients' lives.
في حياة المرضى
He recast the very purpose of medicine.
لقد أعاد صياغة الهدف الأهم من الطب
The goal wasn't to make patients better;
لم يكن الهدف هو جعل المرضى أفضل،
it was to make patients feel better.
بل كان جعل المرضى يشعرون بأنهم أفضل.
He pushed his pain agenda for decades,
لقد ناضل من أجل برنامجه للألم لعقود،
before it finally took hold in the mid-'70s.
قبل أن يتم اعتماده في منتصف السبعينيات
Hundreds of pain clinics sprung up all over the world.
تشكلت المئات من عيادات الألم في كل أنحاء العالم
But as they did -- a tragic twist.
و بفعلهم كان ذلك تحولا جذريا.
Bonica's years of wrestling caught up to him.
سنوات بونيكا من المصارعة بدأت تطارده.
He had been out of the ring for over 20 years,
لقد كان بعيدًا عن الحلبة لأكثر من 20 عامًا
but those 1,500 professional bouts had left a mark on his body.
ولكن هذه ال1500 مباراة احترافية قد تركت علامة في جسده
Still in his mid-50s, he suffered severe osteoarthritis.
عندما كان في منتصف الخمسينيات من عمره، كان يعاني من التهاب شديد في المفاصل
Over the next 20 years he'd have 22 surgeries,
وعلى مدار ال20 عام التاليين، أجرى 22 عملية جراحية
including four spine operations,
متضمنين 4 عمليات في العمود الفقري،
and hip replacement after hip replacement.
واستبدال لعظام الحوض مرة بعد أخرى
He could barely raise his arm, turn his neck.
كان بالكاد يرفع ذراعه ويدير رقبته
He needed aluminum crutches to walk.
واحتاج ركائز من الالومنيوم لكي يمشي.
His friends and former students became his doctors.
أصدقاؤه وطلابه السابقين أصبحوا أطباءه
One recalled that he probably had more nerve-block injections
ذكر أحدهم أنه ربما تناول عدد من حقن الخدر العصبي
than anyone else on the planet.
أكثر من أي أحد آخر على وجه الأرض
Already a workaholic, he worked even more --
كونه مخلص لعمله، كان يعمل حتى لأكثر من
15- to 18-hour days.
15 إلى 18 ساعة يوميًا
Healing others became more than just his job,
علاج الآخرين أصبح أكثر من مجرد وظيفة له
it was his own most effective form of relief.
لقد كان العلاج الأكثر فعالية بالنسبة له
"If I wasn't as busy as I am," he told a reporter at the time,
أخبر صحفيًا ذات يوم "إن لم أكن مشغولًا كما أنا"
"I would be a completely disabled guy."
"لكنت شخصًا معوقًا بالكامل"
On a business trip to Florida in the early 1980s,
وفي رحلة عمل إلى فلوريدا في أوائل الثمانينات
Bonica got a former student to drive him to the Hyde Park area in Tampa.
طلب بونيكا من تلميذ سابق له أن يقله إلى الهايد بارك في تامبا
They drove past palm trees and pulled up to an old mansion,
قاده عبر أشجار النخيل وأوصله إلى منزل قديم
with giant silver howitzer cannons hidden in the garage.
بقاذف صواريخ فضي عملاق مخبأ في المرآب
The house belonged to the Zacchini family,
المنزل كان ينتمي لعائلة الزاكيني
who were something like American circus royalty.
والتي كانت شيئًا يشبه ملكية السيرك الأمريكي
Decades earlier, Bonica had watched them,
من عقود سبقت، كان بونيكا يشاهدهم
clad in silver jumpsuits and goggles,
يرتدون ملابس القفز الفضية والنظارات
doing the act they pioneered -- the Human Cannonball.
في العرض الذي ترودوه، الصاروخ البشري
But now they were like him: retired.
ولكنهم الآن مثله، متقاعدين
That generation is all dead now, including Bonica,
كل هذا الجيل ميت الآن، بما فيهم بونيكا
so there's no way to know exactly what they said that day.
لذلك ما من طريقة لمعرفة ما قالوه بالضبط في ذلك اليوم
But still, I love imagining it.
ولكني لازلت أحب أن أتخيله
The strongman and the human cannonballs reunited,
الرجل القوي والصواريخ البشرية يجتمعون من جديد
showing off old scars, and new ones.
يظهرون الندوب القديمة والجديدة
Maybe Bonica gave them medical advice.
وربما أعطاهم بونيكا نصيحة طبية.
Maybe he told them what he later said in an oral history,
ربما أخبرهم بما قاله لاحقًا في التاريخ المُقال
which is that his time in the circus and wrestling deeply molded his life.
وهو أن الفترة التي قضاها في السيرك والمصارعة شكّلت حياته بعمق
Bonica saw pain close up.
لقد رأي بونيكا الألم عن كثب
He felt it. He lived it.
أحسه. عاشه.
And it made it impossible for him to ignore in others.
وهذا جعله من المستحيل أن يتجاهله في الآخرين
Out of that empathy, he spun a whole new field,
ونتاجًا لهذه العاطفة، أدار مجالًا جديدًا كليًا
played a major role in getting medicine to acknowledge pain
لعب دورًا عظيمًا في جعل الطب يعترف بالألم
in and of itself.
منه وبسببه
In that same oral history,
وفي نفس التاريخ المُقال
Bonica claimed that pain
وضح بونيكا أن الألم
is the most complex human experience.
هو التجربة البشرية الأكثر تعقيدًا
That it involves your past life, your current life,
التي تتضمن حياتك الماضية، والحالية
your interactions, your family.
تفاعلاتك و عائلتك
That was definitely true for Bonica.
لقد كان هذا صحيحًا بالطبع لبونيكا
But it was also true for my mom.
ولكنه صحيح أيضًا لأمي
It's easy for doctors to see my mom
إنه من السهل على الأطباء أن يروا أمي
as a kind of professional patient,
كنوع من المرضى الاحترافيين
a woman who just spends her days in waiting rooms.
امرأة تمضي أيامها في غرف الإنتظار
Sometimes I get stuck seeing her that same way.
وأحيانًا أقع في شرك رؤيتها بنفس الطريقة.
But as I saw Bonica's pain --
ولكن عندما رأيت ألم بونيكا..
a testament to his fully lived life --
كوصية لحياته التي عاشها بالكامل..
I started to remember all the things that my mom's pain holds.
بدأت أتذكر كل الأشياء التي يحملها ألم أمي
Before they got swollen and arthritic,
قبل أن يتورموا ويلتهبوا،
my mom's fingers clacked away
أصابع أمي كانت قد طقطقت
in the hospital H.R. department where she worked.
في قسم الموارد البشرية بالمشفى الذي كانت تعمل فيه
They folded samosas for our entire mosque.
لقد قدموا سمبوسة لمسجدنا بالكامل.
When I was a kid, they cut my hair,
عندما كنت طفلًا، قصوا شعري
wiped my nose,
مسحوا أنفي,
tied my shoes.
ربطوا حذائي.
Thank you.
شكرًا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)